[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
what we're talking about for the
next well several weeks in any case are
the structure of the laws of physics
period the laws of physics all have a
common
theme to them a common uh I shouldn't
say an underlying basis but a common
form laws of physics first of all I to
say what I mean by the laws of physics
there are some laws which are
mathematical laws 1+ 1 is two I don't
regard that particularly as a law of
physics there are laws of probability
Theory the fact that probability Works
altogether may be a law of physics I'm
not sure but uh I don't regard the laws
of probability Theory as laws of physics
you know they're not specific laws of
physics all of the laws of physics such
as FAL ma such as
uh uh the laws of motion of a particle
in a gravitational field the laws of
electricity and magnetism the laws of
charged particles moving in electric and
magnetic fields all these classical laws
of physics oh just the Collision of
billiard balls any such things all of
those laws of physics have a common form
and the common form is the principle of
least
action the laws of thermodynamics for
example which are usually not phrased in
the form of mechanical laws involving a
principle of least action the laws of
thermodynamics are simply the
statistical laws of large numbers of
degrees of freedom given that the basic
laws of those degrees of freedom have
the form of the principle of least
action
the second law of Thermodynamics is
partly a law about probability and
partly a law sort of metal
law uh that whose underlying nature it
is is that the laws of physics derive
from a principle of least action so
we're going to be talking again today
about the principle of least action but
before I do as is my habit I will talk a
little just some very Elementary
mathematical
rules
when I said that I expected you to know
some calculus or at least at minimum to
have having Remembered at least at one
time have known some C calculus I also
decided that I would teach as I went
along all the basic mathematics it's
really needed beyond the most Elementary
things so um what we're going to need
tonight are two little theorems the
first theorem is the integ the theorem
of integration by parts most most of you
probably know about integration by parts
but since it's something we will use I
will derive
it first of all suppose you have some
integral and let's make the independent
variable be T
DT it goes from T1 to
T2 some function but the function itself
happens to be the derivative of some
other function DF or just ordinary
derivative will
here we don't need it to be partial
derivative DF by
DT what is this
integral the integral of a
derivative is simply the function back
again F but the in that's the indefinite
integral the indefinite integral of a
derivative is just a function itself but
the definite integral from T1 to T2
excuse me from T1 T2 of a derivative is
just the difference of the function f at
the two end points of
integrational F at
T2 minus
F at
T1 the easiest way to see this is just
to uh just to think about what the
integral of a function is it's the sum
of little incremental values of the
function but the incremental values what
is uh what does the derivative mean the
derivative just means the difference of
the function at neighboring points so
this might be F at 2 minus F
at1 divided by a little incremental DT
and then the next interval is plus F at
3 - F at
2 plus f at4 - F AT3 and so forth
everything cancels out except the first
and last
term F of two cancels out F of three
cancels out they all cancel out except
the last one and the first one and so
the integral of a derivative is just a
difference of the function at the end
points of the
integration that's number
one now step number two let's suppose
the function f is actually the product
of two functions
f is equal to the product of little F of
T * G of
T of course every function can be
written as a product of some functions
but let's be specific capital F is the
product of little F of T and G of T now
what is the derivative of f with respect
to T it's the sum of two terms so let's
write that as F Doan
derivative is equal to F do little F do
of T *
G Plus F of T * g dot of T this is the
rule for taking the derivative of a
product derivative of the first Factor
time the second plus the derivative of
the second Factor times the first so
let's apply that rule up there F do just
means the FDT and what it tells us is
that the integral from T1 to
T2
of f do
G Plus FG dot notice the structure of
the two terms one of them is a
derivative times a thing which is not
differentiated and the other is the the
opposite uh the opposite uh
uh structure where the second term is
differentiated the first term is not
well according to the Top Line That's
equal to the product
FG at one end point minus FG at the
other end point let's make a notation
for this the standard notation for this
difference is just to write F of
T T2 T1 that's the standard notation for
the difference of of a function at two
end
points so we can write that this is the
difference of a function at two end
points the difference of the product of
the functions at two end points oops T
T1 T2 and
T1 now
yes hav
before the integral of DF DT yeah
whenever you write an integral there
always has to be a d
something the FDT is just a
function
good some people I won't comment on
whether it was a stupid question or not
but I will say please ask me questions
like that you know when you get a little
confused about something like that uh
just stop me slow me down ask me the
question and uh
uh and and force me to make things
explicit in this one
here this is the one you're talking
about right yeah so there should be a DT
in that
one all right now let's take a special
case the special situation is where
either F or G vanishes is equal to zero
at the end
points that's a special case which will
come up time and time again where for
one reason or another either F or G is
equal to zero at the two end points it
could be F being zero at both end points
it could be G being zero at both end
points or it could be some mixed
case uh but in any case if F or G
vanishes at the end points then this is
just zero
so say it again say it again as the
product is the same at the end even
that's good enough even that's good
enough but in the special cases we'll be
doing as a rule one of these two will
always be
zero and so that's not there all right
then we can write this formula in the
form that uh is usually the integration
by parts formula the
integral and now I won't bother writing
the end points the end points are
implicit I'll just let me write T1 to T2
DT of
f.g now let me transpose this over to
the other side that's equal to minus the
integral same integral from T1 to T2
DT G do
F so you see if if you happen to have an
integral with the integrand the thing
you're integrating happening to be a
product of a derivative times another
function you can interchange which one
is differentiated and which one is not
differentiated but at the expense of a
sign you have to change the sign when
you change the place where the dot
goes again that only is
true if the product FG
well I was going to say if the product
FG is equal to zero at the end points as
long as the difference is zero at the
end points but uh that's a fine
point so this is one small
theorem another small theorem it's an
even smaller theorem it's hardly worth
calling a
theorem our expose the integration by
parts again when we need
it another little piece of
mathematics this one is so trivial it's
hardly worth even uh mentioning but I'm
going to mention it anyway supposing I
have a function let me call it a of
T and here's what I know about a of
T I know that when it's integrated let's
suppose it's defined again on an
interval from T1 to T
to AF is some
function on the
interval here's what I know about it I
know about that when it's
integrated with any function any other
function f of T when you multiply it by
any function of
T this can be any
function if you take any function
multiply it by a of T and integrate it
let's suppose that we know that the
answer is
zero that's a lot to know that no matter
what function you put here if you
multiply it by a and you integrate it
you get zero what does that tell you
about
a it tells you that a is zero and the
easy way to see that is say if it's true
for any
function let's check that a of T has to
be zero at some specific point let's
take this specific point over here then
all we have to do is to take a function
f of T which is zero everywhere except
in the vicinity of that little
point then when we multiply the function
a by this little blip let's call that
the blip function when we multiply it by
the blip function we of course get
something proportional to a at that
point and so what we'll get is something
proportional to a at the point where the
blip function is non
zero well by choosing the blip function
to be
anywhere we then prove that a of T has
to be zero
everywhere so if we have a function
which when multiplied by an arbitrary
function the integral is always zero
then that function a must be zero
exactly
zero this
implies that a is
zero now you can't check this by
integrating it with a specific
function if you just take some
particular function and you do the
integral and find it zero that only
tells you a limited amount of
information but if you can prove now you
how long how long does it take you to
integrate it with every possible
function forever so this is not
something you do by hand that's not long
enough that's probably not long enough
uh
so as a rule you don't actually check
this by going through a family of
functions you prove that a of T * F of T
always integrates to zero okay now we're
ready for
the for the the big
one the big
one is the relationship between the
principle of least
action which is a global statement let
me say what I mean by a global statement
we're interested in this trajectories or
histories if you
like histories of systems the system is
described by a set of coordinates that
we can call Q q1 Q2 and so
forth and the trajectory or the history
of the system is a trajectory as a
function of
time time I take upward here I took time
to be horizontal I apologize for that
but
uh the problem is that in elementary
mathematics the independent variable is
always taken to be along the horizontal
axis in physics the independent variable
which is usually of time is always taken
to be the vertical axis so um we
uh we have
to tilt our heads every now and then to
see perspective okay so that's T and uh
a trajectory or a history of a system is
a trajectory as a function of T of all
of the qes The Q's being the coordinates
in other words it's a set of functions
q1 of q1 of T Q2 of
T Q3 of T all of the various generalized
coordinates that describe the system if
you know them as a function of time then
you know the history we're interested in
the histories of
systems the trajectories there's two
ways of going about formulating the laws
of physics one I will call local local
means you concentrate on a location
along the trajectory and you construct a
law which tells you how to go forward at
each point in other words given a bit of
information somewhere along the
trajectory it tells you how to go a
little bit forward FAL ma is an example
it tells you the acceleration in terms
of the position so in that case you need
to know what do you need to know in that
case you need to know the q's and the Q
dots and if you know the q's and the Q
dots then FAL ma will take you to the
next point and the next point and the
next point and will eventually build up
the whole trajectory for you FAL Ma I
call a local law of physics local in the
sense that it makes reference only to a
little bit of the trajectory a
differentially small amount of the
trajectory the other way of describing
the laws of physics is through a global
call This Global a global formulation
which looks at the whole trajectory and
says there's some quantity called the
action which is dependent on the entire
trajectory which is minimized for the
true trajectory for the true trajectory
the one that actually describes the
system the action is minimized and for
that all you have to give
again twn points how many how many
things you have to know you have to know
two things for each coordinate the Q and
The Q dot again you need to know two
things for each Q you need to know Q at
the beginning of the trajectory and you
need to know Q at the end of the
trajectory these are two different
formulations of laws of physics and they
are related in fact they're not only
related they are equivalent to each
other if properly formulated now how do
you see that a global law like the
principle of least action is related to
a local law and it's not very hard you
just focus in on a little piece of the
trajectory here focus in on a little
piece of the
trajectory and say I if I know the
trajectory has gone through this point
and if I know that it's Le through that
point let's suppose I do know that it
went through these two points then the
principle of least action tells me that
it must go along a trajectory between
these two points which minimizes the
action between these two
points in other words if it minimizes
the entire action it must also minimize
the action locally between two
neighboring points because if you chose
a trajectory in
here which didn't minimize the action
between these two points then it also
wouldn't minimize the total action
so there is a relationship between the
global laws and the local laws in
particular if I give you the law of
physics in the form of a least action
principle we should be able to derive
from it a differential equation which
describes an analogous to FAL ma that's
what I want to do now
all right there's a few steps
involved and it's
probably the hardest definition of
derivation that we will have had up till
now but it's not very
hard all right what I'm going to do is
I'm going to take let's call Q of T Q of
T stands for the actual trajectory that
the system really takes the solution for
the
problem and it's not just one Q of t
it's q1 of T dot dot dot dot dot up to q
n of T where n represents the total
number of coordinates that it takes to
describe the system if it's a system of
particles then n is three times the
number of
particles so that's our trajectory and
it's represented by this red line here
now let's take let's change the
trajectory a little bit deform it a
little bit move it a little bit by
taking each Qi of
T and adding to
it a number alpha alpha can be any
number times a specific F sub I of T
let's invent a set of
functions arbitrary set of functions
doesn't matter what they are let's
invent an arbitrary set of functions F
subi of T again n of them and let's add
them to Q sub I of t with a coefficient
Alpha we're going to change
Alpha uh but this F of I of T could be
anything what happens to the trajectory
oh and one other point we're going to
require that the trajectory passes
through the initial point and the final
point that means that fi of T should be
zero at the initial point and the final
point right so fft is to vanish at the
initial point and the final
Point well I've erased it you can get
the drift something is Vanishing at the
initial point and the final point so we
can write that fi of T
fi = Z
at T1 and at
T2 what does the trajectory look like if
we shift it a little bit well it'll be
shifted that's what will happen it will
be
shifted at each point T it'll be shifted
a little
bit by an amount which is proportional
to
Alpha but also proportional to the set
of functions fi of T so it's a little
bit of a shift of the trajectory I've
drawn it as though it was just a shift
to the right it's not a shift to the
right it's a shift in some more
complicated
[Music]
set of directions depending on the FI of
T each of the FIS is shifted a little
bit by an amount proportional to Alpha
that gives us a new trajectory a fake
not a fake trajectory but a trajectory
which is not a solution of the
equations let's calculate the
action of the original true
trajectory
and let's call it the action of the true
trajectory a
of the
q's when I shift the when I shift The
Q's a little
bit a becomes a function of
alpha why because the new trajectory
depends on Alpha and in general whatever
the action is it will depend on the
trajectory so a becomes a function of
alpha forget the fact that it's a
function of Q it becomes a function of
alpha for a given problem with a given
true trajectory and a given set of FS of
I a is just a function of alpha it's a
function of the amount that you shifted
the trajectory the amount can be
positive it can be negative if you shift
if a positive shift of alpha shifts the
trajectory to the right then a negative
shift of alpha shifts the trajectory to
the
left well let's suppose we know that the
action is minimized for the true
trajectory the true trajectory
corresponds to Alpha equals
0 that's unshifted completely unshifted
the true trajectory is Alpha equal Z it
says that a of alpha is minimized at
Alpha equals z that's what the principle
of least action says in fact it says it
for every possible collection of
functions fi no matter how you form the
trajectory if the true trajectory is the
minimum of the action it says that any
FS a of alpha will be minimized when
Alpha is equal to
zero that says in turn that the
derivative of a with respect to
Alpha is equal to zero when Alpha is
equal to
zero for Alpha equals
z it says any change in the traj
parameterized by an alpha increases the
action and so that tells us that a is
stationary at Alpha equals z now if
that's not clear stop me and I'll uh
I'll explain a little more this is one
of the
central is separate definition for the
action we're going to talk yeah I I
thought I talked about it a little bit
last time but I'm going to come back to
it now yeah yeah right so let's now talk
about so far all I said is suppose
there's a thing called the action which
is minimized for the true
trajectory now what is this thing that
we call Action it must somehow be
connected to Newton's equations because
after all content is supposed to be the
same as Newton's equations well I'll
tell you what it is right now the action
is an integral along the trajectory
integral
DT from T1 from the starting point T1 to
the end point
T2 of a thing that's called
l l stands for
lran Lan was named for
lrange was of course a
Frenchman I
think must have been a
Frenchman Itali was Italian
okay oh no no no he was that's why they
call the
Grand was he really Italian yes oh
okay
okay the French claim him the Italians
claim
okay so he was like the PO you
sure like
Napoleon well he was Coran
oh Columbus yeah no no no no nobody
nobody ever said Columbus was
prank L lran and what does the Lan
depend on it depends on the things that
determine the
trajectory it depends on Q of T all of
them Q sub I of
T let's just call it Q of T which means
all of the q's of T but also the
velocity
the position at every time and the
velocity at every time Q
dot so here
this I haven't told you what the lran is
in in specific terms yet have I I I
actually have the last time um I'll just
remind you it is equal to the kinetic
energy minus the potential energy the
kinetic ener energy typically is a
function of velocities the potential
energy is usually a function of
positions so L will be equal to this but
we'll check that we'll we'll for the
moment L could be any
function of position and velocity and
the action is the
integral in other words it's the sum all
along the trajectory of little
incremental actions from one point to
the next little incremental actions
depend on the position and velocity
along here along here along here and so
forth you add them all up and that's the
total
action a
definition so far I'm not even going to
use the fact that it's T minus U I'm
just going to leave it to be any
function of Q and Q
do the question is how do we find the
trajectory which minimizes its action
this is a problem in the calculus of
variations it's a problem that's called
the calculus of variations why is it
called V what's what's being varied
what's being varied is the trajectory we
changed the trajectory a little bit and
we require that the true trajectory is
the one which gives us the least
action all right so this is the action
and of course it does depend on Alpha
because Q depends on Alpha in fact let's
calculate let's uh let's write out one
or two equations over here first what's
the
derivative here's
let's write it this way Q sub I is equal
now let me put a little symbol over this
a little hat this indicates that this is
the true solution to the mathematical
problem of finding the correct
trajectory so let's call one of these
trajectories Q with a little hat I just
put the little hat on it to indicate
that it is the true
trajectory the Hat indicates we've
solved the problem then we add a little
bit to the true trajectory Alpha F of T
and that gives us something that I'll
call Q without a hat on top of it we
could even think of Q as a function of
alpha it is a function of
alpha Q at any instant of time is a
function of alpha because it depends on
Alpha now what's the derivative of
Q subi with respect to
Alpha it's just an ordinary derivative I
don't need to WR derivative the
derivative of Q sub I with respect to
Alpha well we just look at this this
doesn't depend on Alpha this does depend
on Alpha so the derivative of Q subi
with respect to Alpha is just fi of
T the change in Q when you change Alpha
is just fi of
T what about the
change in the
velocity how does the velocity change
when you change Alpha a little bit well
the change in the velocity the changing
Q dot if you shift Alpha is just F
dot we can write down here Q
dot isal to Q hat
dot Plus Al F do I'm assuming
incidentally that Alpha is just a
number just a number doesn't depend on
time it's just a fixed
number fix it once and for all and then
we're going to study the answer as a
function of that
number
the the
uh the change in Q dot when we change
Alpha is just F Dot
all right so the change in Q with
respect to Alpha is f and the change in
Q dot with respect to Alpha is just F
dot let's find out now how much the
action changes how much does the action
change when you vary Alpha a little bit
let's just differentiate it d a by the
alpha keep in mind what an integral
means it just means a sum of
terms it just stands for a sum along the
trajectory so integral DT none of these
things depend on Alpha the thing that
depends on Alpha is the Q and The Q dots
right so how do we find out how much the
action
changes the integral that's still
there the lran will change a little bit
because the q's and the Q dots change
for example the lran changes because Q
changes Q sub I
change in the Lan when you change Q subi
times the change in Q subi when you
change
Alpha so that's F sub I of
T this is the change in the lran due to
a small change in Q times the change in
Q when you change Alpha but that's not
all there is to it l also depends on Q
do so we have to add to it the change in
in when Q dot
changes times the change in Q do which
is f do which is f do of
T this is the change in the
action when you change Alpha a little
bit you want a sum I there yeah you want
a sum over
I thank
you all I've youed is that the change in
an object is equal to the change in each
one of its arguments times the change in
the
argument summed over all of the all of
arguments arguments meaning the sense of
the independent and the independent
variables all right so that's that's a
little
exercise this you should be able to
uh looks a little bit complicated but
it's actually not very complicated we
just differentiated each one of things
inside L and multiplied by the amount
that that thing
changes okay now here we have a term
that has an F of t in it remember F of T
could be any function at all with one
restriction that it vanishes at the end
points remember we're not allowed to
move the end points the end points are
nailed in
place right but here we have F dot I
really would much prefer to have F there
then I would have both of these terms
multiplying an arbitrary
function what's the trick to turn this
into f
f integration by parts you can take the
one which is differentiated it which is
differentiated and
undifferentiated if you take the one
which is undifferentiated and
differentiate it all right but you also
have to change the
sign so let's just work on this I won't
bother rewriting it let's just work on
it we're going to undiff this F at the
cost of differentiating this whole thing
here I think I better I think I'd be
best off to rewrite
it you know you got this
G I mean yes do substition I'm going to
what is g first of all what is g and
what is f f is just
F but G is DL by DQ dot I'm not fiddling
around with this term I'm only fiddling
with this term here and for this term d
l by theq dot plays the role of
G we have F dot time
G okay so let's put a red circle around
the thing that I'm identifying as G and
a red circle around G over
here okay so what do I get then for the
second term the second term alone the
second term becomes minus integral DT
from T1 to T2
DT and now
F times g
dot that means dot means d by DT d by DT
of the derivative of L with respect to Q
rather complicated looking thing d by
DT of the derivative of Lan with respect
to Q subi do * F sub
I
derivative it's here this is g
dot d by DT of
G and instead of having F dot we now
have F so now we can write both of these
terms both the terms the term coming
from varying Q a little bit and the ter
coming from variant Q do a little bit as
integrals with the arbitrary function f
let's write the whole thing down
now this one came in with a minus
sign this term and the first term was
just d l by
DQ f
i
DT whole thing gets integrated
here again I'll just remind you what it
is this is the term that the action
changed because we changed q a little
bit this is the change in the action
because we changed Q dot a little
bit
what about the what about the
contribution from the end points of the
integral remember there was another term
which was f * g at the end
points they all Vish why do they
vanish uh up there at the top you
stipulated that you want those guys to
we stipulated that the trajectory passed
through the initial final point so that
said that F should be zero at the end
points so there's no contribution
here well what do I what have we
calculated we've calculated the change
in the action with respect to
Alpha change in the action with respect
to
Alpha at Alpha equals z we can now set
Alpha equal Z it doesn't matter it
doesn't even depend on Alpha what's the
rule the rule is that this should be
equal to zero
that's the condition of minimizing
action with respect to
Alpha so this should be equal to
zero notice that the fs can be taken
outside the
bracket oh
uh you're probably aware that there
should be a sum over I
here each term in the sum is f
subi multiplies f subi
this has to be zero for every possible
function FS
ofi all possible ways of deforming the
trajectory why because we're looking for
the trajectory with the minimum action
and soever we deform the trajectory we
should increase the action a little
bit so it follows
then that this integral has to be zero
for every possible
function well what does that imply that
implies that the thing in the curly
bracket here has to be identically
zero so what we've done is we've taken
the condition of least action and we
have converted it to a local statement
at each point along the trajectory at
each point along the trajectory we can
get incidentally this is true for every
combination of functions fub1 FS2 F3 and
so forth that means that every one of
these
Expressions has to be equal to zero for
each I at every point in
time d l by
DQ minus d by DT of d l by DQ
do has to be zero all along the
trajectory this has the form of a local
equation at each point on the
trajectory it's equivalent to the global
statement that the action is
minimum okay now that we this is
incidentally this is called the oiler
lrange
equation for the variational problem of
minimizing the integral of L to T this
is called the oiler lrange equation
Oiler not o not like uh not like the
football team not bad but e u l r
Oiler Oiler
lrange variational
equation and this equation is the heart
of all of classical physics in fact in a
slightly different form well a related
but more sophisticated form it is also
the heart of quantum mechanics in the
form of the find in path to grow every
physics problem known to me or every
physical system known to me probably
known to anybody can be formulated as an
action principle with a
LR okay that doesn't only include
mechanical systems it includes systems
of fields gravitational fields general
relativity String Theory everything has
the form of a variational principle
youing to say a principle of least
action what does it say in in
English what does what say this final
statement here the
O well we're going to I think the best
way to let's come back to what it says
in English after we work out what it
says in specific examples perhaps by the
time we say some specific examples we'll
understand what it says what does it say
what's it
say f equals a
name is that is that English enough
so that's the next thing to do is to
show that in a couple of cases of
Interest it really does produce the
right equation of
motion right but in English really what
it is is it's the equivalence between a
global description of the trajectory and
a local description right the local
description is a differential equation
it's a differential equation as we'll
see we'll work out some examples or it's
a system of differential equations of
the form FAL Ma incidentally just in
terms of some some lingo some
definitions I wonder if there's another
way of
looking looking at the equation which
equation looking at the math you have a
a timea of the
Velocity yeah equating that
to of yeah is there you're asking is
there another way to say it is that
yeah yeah the time derivative of thetive
Lan with respect to a velocity let's
call it is equal to the derivative of
Lan with respect to the corresponding
coordinate all right but I think the
best thing to do let's write let's write
it up here and then work it out for some
examples to see how it works
just
say it
again just in sort ofits analysis
is you can
thinkes asort
of yes and
this so that's sort of pushing forward
along the trajectory and the other
just something at the specific point
right all right let me give you some
names the quantity DL by thei dot notice
that it depends on I so it depends on
which coordinate we're talking about
that has a name it's called first of all
it's got a symbol associated with it
it's usually called Pi sub
I it's the derivative of the
Lan with respect to the
velocity q q
dot so it's a component of
something that's related to the
derivative of Lan with respect to a
component of velocity if you're right
anybody know what the name of this
is It's the momentum canonically
conjugate the
Q the Q sub I or you can just say the
momentum the momentum component which
corresponds to the position component Q
subi if you think of the q's as a bunch
of
positions then the pi sub I are called
the
momenta right now let's all right so
what does this say this says d by DT of
something that I'm calling a momentum is
equal to DL by DQ how about this this
got a
name the generalized Force so this is
this is
the I'll just call it the momentum but
the but it's a it's called the canonical
momentum conjugate or the momentum
conjugate to
Q okay momentum conjugate to
Q for every
Q to Qi thank you right on the other
hand d l by D qi
I is called the generalized force or
generalized component of the
force I won't bother writing component
to get the
idea so what this says is the derivative
of some momentum is equal to some Force
sounds like FAL Ma and it is FAL ma
let's try it out for a specific
lran te minus U let's first do it for a
single
particle one
particle mass m for the Moment One
Direction of space just as simple as
possible problem then T is equal to 12
the mass of the particle time xub I do^
2 just x s Let's uh one one
coordinate the simplest possibility
that's T the kinetic energy X star is of
course just velocity in the in Disguise
minus U of X that's
L what is the Q for this problem I'm not
using the language of Q's at the
moment Q is of course just X so I'm
reserving X now for linear position
along a line but of course it is the Q
for this problem Q is just a generalized
term for any kind of coordinate X is
usually used when we're talking about
rectilinear coordinates or cartisian
coordinates all right let's work out
what this what the what lres equations
say what the oil lrange equations say
first of all what is the L by the now it
becomes the L by the x
dot this is the canonical momentum
conjugate to
X well the L by the X do
here's x dot the only place where X do
appears is just equal to MX do the two
goes away because we have X do s and
when we differentiate with respect to x
dot that just gives us MX do that is
what we usually call the
momentum sometimes called P okay so
here's here's the language when we're
talking about ordinary coordinates along
lines X Y and Z we use the language X
for momenta we use the language P when
we're talking about more generalized
kind of coordinates we use the language
q and
Pi but in this case Q is X and Pi is
p what does lr's equation say it says d
by
DT of DL by DX do but that's MX
dot is
equal
now WR this's
let's equals d l by DX d l by DX is
minus du by
DX the only place where X appears is in
u x do appears here x appears here so
this is just minus d by DX this should
be familiar this is just f = ma Mass * X
do isalus d by
DX so we successfully reproduced
Newton's equation for a particle with
one degree of Freedom moving along a
line with the potential energy U notice
that had I had I used for the Lan plus
here I would have gotten the wrong sign
in the force law here so the energy
which we haven't talked about yet
tonight very much talked about other
other times but the energy which is t
plus u is not the Lan the Lan is T minus
U and lran is not conserved lran is not
typically not a conserved
quantity as the particle moves along the
orbit in general the lran will change
it's t plus u which doesn't change but
we have to come back to that we want to
derive
we want to derive energy conservation
from this rule here but so far we have
we do have the R's equations okay now
let's go forward a little bit to a many
particle system for many particle system
all we have to do is for each particle
let's have many particles and many
coordinates for each particle three
coordinates for each particle X Y and Z
let's just call it X1 X2 and
X3 but also we have all of the
particles let's lump them all together
and call them X1 dot dot dot dot down to
X N where n is three times the number of
particles say three 3 n but let's just
use use capital N for the total number
of
x's now each particle might have a
different Mass so that means each X do
squared
might have its own mass that goes along
with it of course they'll come in
triplets uh the the mass of a particle
doesn't depend on which way it's moving
but we can think a little more generally
we can imagine a slightly more General
situation where every X do SAR goes with
its own
Mass this would be a mathematical for a
real physical particle of course the
mass doesn't depend on which way it's
moving so in triple they would come
together with the same mass that's all
right we can uh we can extend the
notation a little bit and just write
that the kinetic energy is the sum of
all the coordinates of the appropriate
mass for that
coordinate time x of I do^ 2 /
2 now this doesn't I doesn't just mean 1
2 and
three meaning X Y and Z and it doesn't
just mean which particle we're talking
about it means the collection of all the
different things which specify a
particular coordinate which particle as
well as which
direction and then the potential energy
which is a function of where the
particles
are it's a function of the positions of
the particles just becomes minus some
potential which depends on all of the
particles I didn't have to change it
it's just minus U of x U of X here means
U of all of the
coordinates now in specific instances
you may have some particular special
form and we'll talk about the special
forms that it can have but in a general
context we can imagine a u which just
depends on all of the positions of all
the
particles then what happens if we go
through the same exercise coordinate by
coordinate well the L by the x of I do
becomes M sub I * X I
do we'll call that P
subi this does no sum intended here no
summation intended here so if this is X
Y or Z this could be the X Y or Z
component of a particular particle
momentum but we could also vary which
particle we're talking about and so this
extends not only over the directions of
space but which particle we're talking
about there are three in momenta and
three in
positions each equation then takes the
form of the time
derivative of the momentum of a
particular direction in a particular
particle is equal to the force the
component of the force associated with a
particular particle and the particular
direction of
space this again is FAL ma FAL ma for
each particle at each direction of
space so
uh X the U by the x
i the
implication is that this must be very
very general after all all this is is a
collection of particles with Force laws
the force laws happening to be just such
to hold it together into an
eraser you're nothing but a collection
of particles held together by
forces this is an extremely
General system that we're talking about
here and it is definitely governed by a
principle of least action the principle
of least action being gotten by taking
ke minus by taking kinetic energy minus
potential
energy so we see
already that the principle of least
action is General enough to cover just
about every possible mechanical system
we could think about because every
mechanical system we could think about
we could imagine being made out of
chunks of material which in turn are
made of uh collections of particles held
together by interatomic forces or
whatever holds the system together let's
do a couple of examples just to see how
things
work Let's do an example of two
particles on a line
interacting with a force between them
governed by a potential
energy all right so we
have two particles on a
line particle one has coordinate X1
particle 2 has coordinate
X2 particle one has mass
M1 particle 2 has mass
M2 now there's also a potential energy
function the potential energy is a
function of both
coordinates if there's a force between
the two
particles and the two particles
influence each other then you would
expect in general that the potential en
will depend on the position of both
particles maybe in some complicated way
now I want to take a I want to focus on
a particular situation and the
particular situation is one which has
what I'll call what everybody calls
translation in
variance translation invariance means
that for our purposes now the lran or
let's say in particular the potential
energy would not change if you moved
both particles together
in other words it doesn't depend on
where the particles are it does depend
on the distance between
them this assumption is equivalent to a
symmetry the Symmetry being I'll explain
what I mean by a symmetry in a moment
more generally but the Symmetry being
translation
symmetry nothing depends on where you
put the origin of coordinates things
only depend on the distance between
particles which is another way of saying
that if you move the whole
system if you translate it translation
means moving it rigidly everything being
kept at the same
distance that in this case the lran
would not
change uh the velocities don't change if
you just take a particle moving with a
given velocity given velocity moves
means it moves a certain distance in a
certain time if you change both the
initial position and the final position
by the same amount then the velocity
doesn't
change in other words if uh if your car
goes one mile in uh in uh 10 seconds W
that's fast
now but uh you move it ahead by a
certain distance and you keep the
velocity the same then it's still going
one mile you know what I mean velocity
itself doesn't depend on the choice of
coordinates on the choice of
origin why well let's think of X of T
and let's add a constant to X of T just
add a constant to it if you add a
constant to it it doesn't change the
time derivative of x so shifting
everything by a constant amount would
change none of the
velocities and if the potential energy
only depends on the distance between
them then the PO poal energy doesn't
change if you rigidly move everything
under those circumstances the lran has
or the system has a symmetry it doesn't
change if you if you move everything by
the same
amount so specifically then in that case
the lran for this two particle system
would be kinetic energy M1 X1 do^ 2 / 2
plus N2 X2 do^ 2 / 2 those are the
kinetic energies and then the potential
energy
minus and the potential energy now is
assumed to only depend on the distance
between X1 and X2 so it only depends on
X1 minus
X2 now this would not be the case if
there was a large lump of matter out
here that happened to be exerting forces
on both X1 and
X2 then the potential might also depend
on how close you were to that lump of
matter it wouldn't just depend on the
distance between them it would also
depend on the distance to a big lump
over here but if the only system if the
system is a closed
system containing only two parts and
it's translation invariant meaning to
say everything everything stays stays
the same if you shift everything then
the potential energy can only be a
function of the distance between the two
points X1 -
X2 absolute
value actually it doesn't have to be
absolute value but we could make it
absolute value if we want if we wanted
it to be literally the distance between
the two points then uh then we would
make it absolute
value uh but uh for my purposes right
now it's good enough that it's just a
function of the of the separation the X1
- X2 that's good enough that's
translation and varing that means that
if we were to add a constant to each X
the same constant to each X nothing
would change the velocities wouldn't
change because the velocity doesn't
depend on C and X1 minus X2 wouldn't
change because the constant translation
would cancel out all right so this is a
symmetry this is the case of translation
symmetry
let's work out now MC's equations
there's an equation for X1 there's an
equation for X2 the equation for X1 is d
by
DT write out D by
DT of partial of L with respect to X1
dot equals partial of L with respect to
X1
all right d by DT of partial LEL with
respect to X1 dot that's just ma for the
first particle right that's just that's
just d by DT of
P1 P1 by DT P1 being the momentum of
particle
one the L by the X1 dot is just mx1 dot
that's the momentum and so the first the
equation for the first particle starts
with d P1 by DT is equal to D L by
dx1 all right the only thing that
depends on X1 is U and so that becomes
is equal to minus du by
dx1 what about the second particle
that's particle number one let's do
particle number two now the
P2
by
DT that just comes from
here that's going to equal minus
V by D
X2 what's the relation between the U by
dx1 and D by
dx2 they're equal and
opposite
if a thing only depends on the
difference of two variables like this
then the derivative well let's just look
at it the derivative of U with respect
to X1 is just the derivative of U with
respect to the
argument is it not is it obvious to
everybody that the derivative with
respect to X2 is minus the derivative
with respect to X1 if it's obvious to
everyone I won't explain
it yes okay um uh it's ah okay all right
so let's let's let's do it then we have
a function which only depends on X1 -
X2 now let's just call let's just call
this variable X1 - X2 let's give it a
name let's call it X so U is only a
function of
x no let's not call it X let's call it B
for
difference D for difference so U is a
function of d d is X1 -
X2 all right let's calculate first of
all the derivative of U with respect to
X1 by the chain rule the derivative of U
with respect to X1 is the derivative of
U with respect to D remember U is really
only a function of D times the
derivative of D with respect to X1
what's the derivative of D this is D X1
- X2 D = X1 -2
what's the derivative of B with respect
to
X1 one so this is just du by
DD what's the derivative of U with
respect to
X2 that's du by
DD times the change in D when you change
X2 what's the change in U when you
change X2
what's the change in D when you change
X2 minus one the derivative of D with
respect to X2 is minus one so there's a
minus sign between
them derivative with respect to one
variable is minus the derivative with
respect to the other
variable that's as a consequence of the
fact that it only depends on between
there
well the implication seems to be
Newton's law of action and reaction and
it is the fact or the assumption that
the potential energy only depends on the
distance between them or difference
between the two variables that it's
translation invariant that there's a
translation symmetry that's equivalent
to the statement that the force on
particle one is minus the force on
particle
what's the net result the net result is
momentum conservation if you add these
two
equations to find DP total P1 + P2 by
DT then the forces on the right hand
side will cancel just as they do just as
Newton assumed that they
were so what we find from this is that
momentum conservation for this simple
system here is a consequence of trans
ation in
variance it's a consequence of
translation and variance number one and
number two the form of the equations and
the fact that they derive from uh uh
from the principle of the elast
action we we we're going to explore this
more thoroughly so far this is just an
example and it's an example of the
relationship this is really really
important this maybe the most important
thing that you can learn tonight or that
you could learn about theoretical
physics practically is the connection
between symmetries and conservation laws
here's the first example of the relation
between a symmetry translation and
variance in
space and a conservation law which is
the conservation of
momentum symmetry says that you only
depends on X1 -
X2 from that it follows that the force
on particle one is minus the force on
particle two and from that follows
conservation of momentum conservation of
linear momentum we'll call
it so this is the first
example and we'll see more of them of
conservation laws and their
relationships to
symmetries as I said this is a very very
deep underlying theme of of of physics
of theoretical physics that every
has associated with it a conservation
law what does a symmetry mean a symmetry
means an active operation that you can
do on the system for example translating
it which does not change the lran which
does not change the value of the lran or
better yet the value of the
action if the action of a system does
not change when you do a transformation
of some type in this case just moving
everything to the right by a fixed
amount uh that is a symmetry of the
particular action that we're talking
about every time the action has a
symmetry there is associated with it a
conservation law this is the simplest
example of that and the first first of
many examples that I hope we'll
see over the next
um however long we pursue this
question's the which is inversions ah
yes yes very
good in particular there would be an
inversion symmetry If This Were a
function only of the absolute value yeah
okay In classical
mechanics that's called a discrete
symmetry A continuous symmetry is one
that you can imagine doing a little bit
or a lot we'll talk about this
difference between discrete symmetries
and uh continuous symmetries but a
discret symmetry is one that depends on
a parameter that could be very small
just a very small shift or very big or
that you could build up the big shifts
out of a lot of little small
shifts that's called a dis a continuous
symmetry a discrete symmetry is an
operation like interchanging two things
which only has a discrete form it's
either one way or the other and there's
nothing interpolating between them uh In
classical mechanics discrete symmetries
don't gener interesting conservation
laws in quantum mechanics they do so but
that's that's for a later uh a later
discussion so you're right it does have
another symmetry in particular if we say
this is a function of absolute of X1 -
X2 this wouldn't have much um oomph much
uh uh implication in classical
mechanics it does have implication in
quantum mechanics implication of a
conservation
okay
um so we just did conservation of
momentum for a simple okay let's do a
couple of more mechanical cases couple
more mechanical systems to get the feel
for this let's do a problem in which a
particle moves in two
Dimensions particle moving near the
surface of the Earth here's the surface
of the Earth here's our particle right
over here uh of course it has three
coordinates associated with it but let's
just take two coordinates X and Y X uh
goes this way y goes vertically
upward the particle is described by two
coordinates there are two Q's now not
because there are two particles but
because there are two directions of
Space X and Y okay the kinetic energy is
12 m x do s + n y do
2 I have assumed that the mass does not
depend on which direction the particle
is
moving we could imagine some sort of
nutty particle who have which have a
larger Mass with respect to Vertical
motion than horizontal motion but I'm
not not doing that now and then what
about the potential energy all right
this is the gravitational potential
energy that I'm talking about the
gravitation in case I haven't said it
before I will tell you now the
gravitational potential energy of an
object near the surface of the
Earth this is not in a situation where
we're far from the surface of the Earth
but near the surface of the Earth is
just proportional to the height to the
elevation right
so uh you subtract the potential energy
the potential
energy is equal to the height of the
particle
y it's proportional to its mass the
heavier the particle the more poal
energy it has when you lift it and it's
proportional to the acceleration of
gravity G 10 m/s per second little G is
10 in metric units and it's just the
strength of the Earth's gravitational
field near the surface of the
Earth okay that's the that's the let's
ask what is the force on a particle the
force on the particle has no X component
because du by DX is equal to
zero du U by d y
is equal to
mg but the force is minus that so minus
the uy Y is minus
mg and the minus sign represents the
fact that the force is downward when we
take the Y AIS to be pointing upward so
it's accelerated
downward all right so let's add now or
subtract as the case may be the
potential energy
mgy now what kind of symmetry does this
problem
have well it has translation symmetry
along the
xais if I change X by a constant it
doesn't change x dot and since the
potential energy doesn't depend on X the
Lan this is Lan the Lan is translation
invariant along the xais it has X
translation how about y translation and
variance does it have y translation in
variance no oh why because of the Y over
here would you ask me
why no for small y for small y
why why for small y
first you stay close to the surface it
doesn't
who's the president of
China excuse me I
think the small y small I don't know I
don't know either when you change why
the leian changes right because of the Y
that's here now notice incidentally uh
let me point something else out we could
add a constant this is something I
should have pointed out a while ago you
can always add a constant to the
potential energy at no cost it changes
none of the physics now that constant
has to be treated as a true constant
throughout the problem it doesn't change
anything because it doesn't change the
force the U by well the U by if you add
a constant it doesn't change any of the
derivatives of U and so it doesn't
change any of the forces it's resets the
zero of potential energy but there's no
physical consequence of adding a
constant to potential energy so it
doesn't matter where you measure the
altitude from whether it's sea level or
whether it's 10 m above sea level or so
forth but if you change y you change
U all right so with that logic we should
find one conservation law not two we
should find one conservation law
associated with X and not the
corresponding conservation law with
respect to Y because there's only one
Symmetry and in fact if we work out the
equations the equations of motion will
be DL by DX do is MX do d by DT of that
that's called ma masstimes acceleration
and that's equal to zero why zero
because U doesn't depend on
X this is just conservation of the X
component of momentum
so the X component of momentum is
conserved but the Y component of
momentum d by DT of myy dot that's the
time derivative of the Y component of
momentum is the derivative of U with
respect to
Y derivative of minus U with respect to
Y so that's equal to minus
mgus mg d by d y isus mg orus d by d y
isus
mg all right so what is this equation
this just tells me that the vertical
acceleration is proportional to the
force of gravity
or uh or that the acceleration is equal
to the acceleration of gravity we can
cancel out the
ncn but notice the important thing is
that there is no conservation of Y
momentum of the Y component of momentum
and that's associated with the fact
there symmetry associated with
translation in the y
direction I'm going to do one more
example of the relationship in
particular the relationship between
symmetries and conservation laws but
also it's an example in which I won't
use rectangular
coordinates
no yes of course but uh the equ You by
no accid this falling body is
exactly equ would get if you did this
with freshman classical physics in a
Mechanics for a falling body well you
wouldn't you would never write this down
in classical physics no no I'm saying
you would say that there isation of
energy the fact that potential energy
and the kinetic energy remain remain
constant so it's I just wanted
reformulation something we probably
already seen the reason yeah so far so
far I haven't even talked about in this
context conservation of energy yeah we
will talk about it and you'll be
perfectly right we'll find that in this
structure there's a conservation not of
kinetic energy minus potential energy
but kinetic energy plus potential energy
so it's going to require an ex step to
see that the energy is conserved and
we're going to want to ask the question
If energy is conserved
is it also conserved because of some
Symmetry and if so what
symmetry so we want to uh we want to
formulate our laws of the basic law of
physics now is that symmetries equal
conservation laws and we're going to
want to see that that that follows from
the form of lr's equations but it's
little little feet for
little little little steps for little
feet um
the principle of lease action does not
really depend on the coordinates that
you used to describe a particle whatever
coordinates you use you could use polar
coordinates you could use rectangular
coordinates you could use parabolic
coordinates you could use some screw
ball coordinates with curved the fancy
curve
the uh axes and so forth you can always
why are those
screw coordinates
are normal coordinates with with curved
axes and so forth um use any coordinates
you like you can rewrite the expression
for the kinetic energy you can rewrite
the expression for the potential energy
it may look more complicated in other
coordinates but you can rewrite the
expression for kinetic energy potential
energy and LR
and you can rewrite the expression for
the action the action may look more
complicated in terms of other
coordinates but it will still be the
same good old action it will depend on
the trajectory and give you the same
answer that you would have gotten
rectangular coordinates if you rewrite
it correctly the fact that the action is
minimized for the correct trajectory is
a statement that doesn't depend on what
coordinates you use so the principle of
least action is a principle that is
coordinate independent it doesn't depend
on the specific coordinates and
therefore you can apply it to any set of
coordinates you use to describe a system
I'm going to show you how you would do
it for Polar coordinates if we were
talking about a particle
again let's take the
case of a particle moving in a
plane and now instead of describing it
by X and Y let's describe by R Anda
distance from the origin R and angle
relative to the
horizontal we have to write the
Lan then we'll write L's equations it's
a system with two coordinates R and
Theta and a trajectory will now consist
of an R of
T and A Theta of
T in other words at every instant of
time the distance from the origin and
the angle that determines the trajectory
of the
particle okay let's work out the kinetic
energy first the kinetic energy is 12
mv^ 2 so what we have to do is we have
to calculate the magnitude of the
Velocity to do that let's temporarily
set up some coordinates at this point
over here at the point of the particle
where one axis is along R and the other
axis points in what I'll call the Theta
Direction sort of along the angular
Direction but temporarily for the moment
let's just think of them as cartisian
coordinates except erected right at this
point then the velocity has two
components one of them is the component
along R and you will not be surprised I
will not work this out for you but you
won't be surprised I think if I tell you
that the component of velocity along R
all right is V subr velocity along the r
direction is just r
do if R is changing then there's a
component of velocity along R it's just
the r dot what about the component of
velocity in the perpendicular Direction
how big is
it you might think it's just Theta
dot this is V along the other
axis I don't want to call it V Theta I'm
just going to call it V along the
perpendicular axis
perpendicular to
R how big is
that it's not Theta
dot but it's R Theta dot how do you see
that well supposing the particle is near
the origin over here and you change
Theta a little bit per unit time then it
moves a little and it has a certain
velocity suppose you change the angle by
the same amount but the distance of the
particle is far away
then it moves a lot more so the further
out you are for a given Theta dot for a
given Theta dot the further out you are
the faster you're moving right the tips
of my fingers is moving faster than my
elow and in fact the velocity is
proportional to how far away you are but
it's also proportional to Theta dot
because if Theta dot was Zero if there
was no change in the angle you would
have no component of velocity along that
direction so these are the two
components of velocity and the kinetic
energy is 12 M time the r component of
the Velocity squar R do
SAR plus 12
M time V perpendicular squar which is R
2 thet do
squ this is the kinetic energy now let's
the potential
energy I'm going to invent a special
kind of potential energy which is called
the central Force Central Force means
that the potential energy only depends
on
distance sorry r. s thank you r. s MV
s so there 12 Mr do 2 and 12 m 2 Theta
do s now let's introduce a potential
energy and let's make the potential
energy that only depend on
R only depend on
distance that's a special case but it's
a special case with symmetry what's the
Symmetry that's involved if I say that
the potential energy only depends on
distance rotational symmetry what that
would say is that nothing changes if I
rotate
everything if the potential energ only
depends on
distance only depends on distance that
means the potential energy does not
change if I rotate the position of the
particle or if I rotate the axis if I
just physically take the particle and
rotate it without stretching R then the
potential energy doesn't change if the
potential energy only depends on
r
theine energy doesn't depend yes but it
doesn't depend on Theta on yeah yeah but
it doesn't it doesn't depends only on
Theta dot so if we change all thetas by
the same amount yeah that's correct we
have to check that uh but as you can see
because it only depends on Theta Dot and
not Theta explicitly then if I shift all
thetas other words I say Theta you know
what I
mean okay so then we have minus U U of
R minus U of
R let's work out now the LR equations of
motion The Q's are R and Theta so all we
have to work out is first of all for R
let's start with r partial of L with
respect to r dot incidentally this is l
l is kinetic minus potential partial of
L with respect to R dot is Mr
dot that's also equal to the momentum
conjugate to
R it's just a radial component of
momentum m r dot or M * the Velocity in
the r Direction not surprisingly that's
the radial component of a linear
momentum right then lr's equations
become d by DT of this which is
d by DT of Mr dot it's also known as
mrble
dot the radial component of acceleration
is
equal to minus du by d
r obviously minus du by d r is the
radial component of force this is just
the radial component of FAL
ma the mass time the second derivative
of R is Du by d r notice that the radial
component of the momentum is not
conserved okay we can write
this as d by
DT of the radial component of momentum
not equal to zero but it's equal to
minus du by Dr
R so there is no conservation of radial
momentum let's look at the angular
equation of motion now the angular
equation of motion the equation of
motion fora
same deal just think of theta as a
generalized
coordinate partial ofel with respect to
Theta dot that's
m² Theta
dot what's the what's its name what's
the name for that
object canonical momentum conjugate to
Theta what's it another name for
it angular
momentum all it is is angular momentum
but we see now angular momentum
arising out of the same pattern DL this
is
DL by D Theta
dot same pattern derivative of L with
respect to Q dot is the momentum
conjugate to Q D L by dot momentum
conjugate to R DL by D Theta dot
momentum conjugate to Theta now now what
is the equation of motion for Thea it's
D by DT of
this D by
DT of m 2 Theta
dot is equal to
what zero zero in this case because U
doesn't depend on Theta by
assumption d by DT of something equals z
that says that that something doesn't
change so this this is an equation of
conservation it's conservation of m 2
Theta dot or conservation of angular
momentum when the force or when the
potential energy doesn't depend on
angle
then then angular momentum is conserved
it's usually called L
incidentally this is usually called
l so it says that L is
conserved in fact that allows us uh that
that gives us a good clue about the
nature of the motion of the system if L
is
conserved let's just see what that says
it says that m 2 Theta dot doesn't
change so it says that
m² Theta dot is equal to a Conant it
doesn't change with time it's whatever
it was when you
began however you began the
motion the angular momentum doesn't
change well you can solve this and write
that
Theta is equal to the constant over
m² so you see what happens as R goes in
and out for whatever reason as R perhaps
either oscillates or gets bigger or gets
smaller Theta dot changes the compens
this is just the uh the the spinning ice
skater effect as R gets
smaller Thea dot gets bigger it's the
conservation of angular momentum but you
see it arises once again from a symmetry
the Symmetry in this case being
rotational
invariance rotational invariance angular
momentum
conservation translation invariance
linear moment linear conservation of
momentum that's the
[Music]
pattern the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu